welcome blue i'm about to play the theme
song
[Music]
hello everyone welcome to actin flab
live stream number 35.0
it is january 4th 2022 so also
happy new year to everyone
welcome to the actinflab
we are a participatory online lab that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome on these live streams and we'll
be following good video etiquette
if you go to
activeinference.org you can find out
more about how to contribute or get
involved because anyone who is curious
and wants to learn more
will have a niche for you and you will
surely learn and create all kinds of
awesome affordances so if you're curious
or you want to learn by doing please
come get involved with actonflab
today in active livestream number 35.0
we are going to be learning and
discussing this paper a tale of two
architectures
free energy its models and modularity by
majeed benny in december 2021
but kind of published in 22
and just like all the other dot zeros
the video we're about to do is just an
introduction and a discussion it's not a
review or a final word and in fact we're
very much looking forward to the two
upcoming weeks when majeed may join us
and hopefully many of you will join us
and we're just gonna have a good time
talk about the paper what did we learn
from it and what are the implications
today we're going to be more focused on
the aims and claims the abstract the
roadmap the background the keywords and
there aren't any figures or formalisms
but we'll go through some of the key
arguments which are very
provocative and very salient
so if you want to get involved just get
in touch and we will
let you know how to participate
let's begin with a little bit of an
introduction and a warm-up so feel free
to say hello and maybe just one thing
that made you excited to discuss this
paper so i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i was excited to
read philosophical work by benny who
always writes very interesting things
and just understand how
architectures of physical systems and
their functional descriptions are
related to the fep
dean
thanks danny i'm dean i'm here in
calgary it's uh
really really cold and snowy
but that's not why we're here
my real question was so what do we do
about this seeming
failure or attraction to the ability to
categorize and so the question is do we
model up
and yeah so reading the paper i
i kind of tried to figure out the answer
to that i'll pass it down to blue
so i like this paper from the
perspective of like multi-scale
dimensionality um
and also modularity like modules at
different dimensions um the scale-free
aspect of the markov blanket and or the
not scale-free aspect of the markov
blanket and anyway i thought it was just
really neat and a cool um
way to fit the pieces together
excellent so
we have
some slide with things that we want to
discuss in the dot one and the dot two
and beyond so at any point feel free to
add information there and we'll be
writing things there so we're not gonna
get to it all we're not gonna make this
a 11 hour video we'll get things down to
discuss in 35.1 and 2.
but we can lead in with
the big question a big question
which is how do we think about
modularity of different kinds like
functional effective and anatomical
which we'll be discussing later
in active inference and free energy
principle
and why does that matter why does it
matter how we think about modularity of
different kinds what does it mean
on this slide are some images related to
just different uses of modularity
just
modules like lego bricks
other times modularity can refer to like
part of a network that's more densely
connected like a click
other times modularity doesn't refer to
hot swap ability but rather to
a larger structure that's composed of
smaller modules
whether they're the same or different
it's often applied to mathematical
systems or biological systems so there's
so many
aspects of modularity and today we're
going to be exploring
what are those aspects of modularity and
why does it matter for the free energy
principle
blue or dean like any thoughts on the
general
modularity question
i got i got a quick question so
for me
when we see these sort of images that we
externalized and artifacts and that sort
of thing
when i got it started getting to the
paper uh the real problem for the
modularity argument is
what does localized mean when we're
talking about
fmri
representations as the tool does a bump
in electrochemical impulse mean a
clearly defined border
i don't think so
of course not
where one bump ends and another begins
all inside the same energy field might
be captured through my fmri imaging and
is that misleading because there's no
moment of stasis because the magnets
inside our heads
keep wearing constantly so that was
again another question
that i
sort of tried to carry on through as i
was reading what the author wrote out
yeah
where are we talking about modules
where are we modularizing
and does that map onto potentially
realism and instrumentalism
any
big setting ideas blue or we can
continue to aims all right
so the paper that we're discussing is by
majeed benny a tale of two architectures
free energy its models and modularity
and it's in the paper consciousness and
consciousness and cognition
just to go through some of the key aims
and claims and then feel free to add a
comment so the paper presents a model
model-based defense of the partial
functional informational segregation of
cognition in the context of predictive
architecture
more specifically to defend the
modularity thesis the paper computes two
counter arguments that lie at the center
of hippolyto and kirchoff's 2019 recent
confitation of the modularity thesis to
confuse is like to refute
the main insight of the paper is that
hippolyto kirchoff's counter arguments
miss the mark because they dismiss a few
rudimentary facts about the model based
nature of dynamical causal models and
markov blankets
so that's why we kind of led in with a
big question about modularity why does
it matter because we're kind of down the
road a little bit like okay modularity
matters it matters how we think about
and analyze and design modular systems
and then
how does it apply to fep
and hipolito and kirchoff make a
computation of the modularity thesis
which we can look at soon
and then benny is firing back
with this current paper so that situates
us like in the biggest scope of thinking
about modularity
h k 2019 and here we are with mdb 2021.
so can i add to that daniel
yeah so
he does we didn't put encapsulation in
here but i know we're gonna talk about
that a bit
but in order to be able to make sure
that we don't mix things up we have to
understand that encapsulation is a
separation of what matters or what we
consider to be a signal from the noise
and i always think back to nate silver
when i try to compare those two things
so it's a momentary on offer it's a
momentary in out not that there's a
walled off section per se
in the brain like we can diagram out or
represent
as a as an artifact
fmri images however might coerce us into
thinking that that's what's happening
that there's actually a walled off
section
when that isn't actually the case to
avoid the cognitive overload
there are break stop mechanisms in our
mind we don't have to tell our pancreas
or basic ganglia what to do
which then assists us in our ability to
take the external states
like these slides in
and i think that's what benny was trying
to point to although
he didn't probably go into that
explanation the way that i just did but
i'm
i'm kind of in defense of this author so
i'm i'm starting off right now i'm in
his corner i'm ready to tag up and climb
in the ring
so just to kind of piggyback onto that
like when you're talking about
encapsulating
it's really talking about drawing a
boundary around something and like isn't
the markov blanket like isn't that the
ability to draw a boundary around
something right so so i don't know like
this encapsulating markov blanketing
boundary drawing like all of those are
conflated in my mind and i don't know if
there's like a separate way to tease
them all apart or if or if i have
cracked correctly grouped them
great
onwards
so
i'll read the first two and then
blue for the second two
the paper presents a model based defense
of the partial functional informational
segregation of cognition in the context
of the predictive architecture
the paper argues that the model
relativeness of modularity does not need
to undermine its tenability
in fact it holds that using models
is indispensable to scientific practice
and it builds its argument about the
indispensability of modularity to
predictive architecture on the
indispensability of scientific models
more specifically to defend the
modularity thesis the paper confused two
counter-arguments that lie at the center
of hippolyto and kirchoff's 2019 recent
confitation of the modularity thesis the
main insight of the paper is that
hippolito and kirchoff's counter
arguments miss the mark because they
dismiss a few rudimentary facts about
the model-based nature of dynamical
causal models and markov blankets
great so
nice
philosophy abstract
here is the roadmap where we are going
and so this has a fun
roadmap there are nine
sections
there's the introduction and then there
are eight sections with uh or dare i say
eight modules
that have kind of interesting names
that we'll be
looking into
and there are not any figures or
formalisms
but the sections are here maybe dean
will rejoin
and uh
welcome back dean
um
i need an ethernet cable
from my heart to yours
um
the keywords
are free energy principle model based
science modularity and then there's dag
directed acyclic graphs
and then dcm
which is going to have two different
unpackings as directed cyclic models
and as dynamical causal models
and we're going to go through these
keywords kind of as they appear in the
paper we're not going to have a separate
section
so let's go right into the introduction
section of the paper
where
we find somewhat of an epistemic
preamble
so not to read the whole thing but benny
belongs to the clan of philosophers with
karnap and kun
who can see that the choice of
theoretical frameworks is not completely
arbitrary
because some pragmatics
affect the choice of theories so okay we
have dispensed with the naive
postmodernist perspective
and more generally benny identifies
as a naturalized metaphysician in the
sense of ladyman and ross
in that metaphysics is worthwhile when
it is informed by our best scientific
theories of the field
so it's kind of just like a classy
co-informing process between
science and metaphysics
and
it is drawing on this work by ladyman
and ross
every thing must go
metaphysics naturalized
and then just like look at the chapter
titles because it's not a
book that i was very familiar with
they're defending science
they're defending a scientific realism
and a structuralism so maybe we're not
going to be in touch with the ultimate
reality but at least we can be in touch
with something that's constructively
empirical and scientifically real
they talk about the unity of science
consilience like eo wilson
and about causation in a world that's
structural but also complex
and so
that's sort of
the preamble
where benny characterizes his own stance
and kind of gives this background that
is quite personal in some ways but then
will lead into our understanding about
the paper and the contributions so
anything to add on that
all i would
try to quantify here is that he's not
starting from a position of did you see
that he's basically starting from a
position of did you see what i see
he holds that as being valuable
great
that takes us to model based science so
as we saw in the chapters
uh of
ladyman and ross
scientists use models
it's kind of like saying we use maps on
territories
and
there's so many kinds of models
a few that we've seen
are for example a graphical
visualization
of a bayesian statistical model and one
example of that is like this partially
observable markov decision process that
we often look at
and what do models do well that's quite
a big topic but they represent
hypotheses
as well as useful models of conceptual
or empirical systems and so there's many
many kinds of models
and some of them can be reflected
graphically
and in that
sentence graphical is referring to
visual like a computer graphic but also
graphical like a graphical network
and so we're going to be talking about
the visual aspects of graphs
but this isn't in a study in aesthetics
this is going to be talking about the
topology of graphs in their network
sense but model-based science is just
the kind of
pragmatic perspective that scientists
use models implicitly and explicitly and
there are certain things that we can say
about those models
anything that either of you would add on
model-based science
i'd want to know who who disagrees who
doesn't think that scientists are using
models like is this just a total
uh
meaningless claim or are are there
controversies related to this
okay so let's look at a few different
types of models
specifically these graphical
models that can be represented by
networks
so one kind of special graphical model
is called a directed acyclic graph or a
dag
and so
dags as their name would have it do not
have cycles amongst variables so nodes
are variables and edges are directed
influences and there are no cycles in
dags
and so it turns out that computing
it's relatively efficient
and it has known algorithms
so here is a
image of a dag that i
got from a 2012 paper in ecology and so
the parameters are defined here and you
can look for more details but just
visually
these are different
modules of the model there's like this
underlying process model there's the
individual covariate model there's an
observation model whatever those things
are
but
one can imagine that you can like start
at the parts that don't have any parents
and then kind of
drip coffee your way to n and y which
are like the ultimate grandchildren
nodes
and then n and y don't feedback to
change the other
upstream parameters so dags
are
not
um all of this exact shape or type but
what makes them in a category is that
they don't have cycles in the way that
the variables are influencing each other
that makes them easy to compute and
relatively straightforward
we can contrast that
with directed cyclic models so we're
still talking about graphical models
here
directed cyclic models or dcm
have causal loops in the graphical
models
and so
this can make certain kinds of
computation more difficult i'm sure
people can think about different ways
that that might happen
the direction of the edges determines
the influence of one random variable on
another
so
if it doesn't have cycles it's a dag
and inference on those dags may be
performed exactly using algorithms such
as belief propagation or variable
elimination
like you can kind of collapse a subtree
into
a simpler system but with cycles it's a
little bit more complex
so
that's the difference between the dag
and the dcm directed cyclic model but
then there's going to be another dcm
coming up later
any comments there
do you think that the
the looping
can can be gets kind of a spiraling kind
of a
an accumulation effect that the dag
model
which with its narrowing and narrowing
and and sort of elimination
focus
benny talks about the fact that they
they're actually complementary but
do do you actually think they're
complementary as well
i think that they
exhaustively describe the landscape of
graphical models because either it has a
cycle or it doesn't but it's quite
literally the difference between like
dropping a coin in a little
machine that just dribbles down and then
playing pinball where you could have all
kinds of
feedback so i think they're mutually
exhaustive
but that may be sort of a deflationary
stance because they're defined as
contrary to each other
um we're not gonna go too into detail
here
but sometimes
um
you want to use a model that is
acyclic even for a cyclic system for
example within one time step it might be
a heuristic approximation to make it a
um
[Music]
dag model directed acyclic model rather
than a cyclic model so we're talking
about our statistical models here not
the topology of how things are connected
in the real world but
i just thought it was very interesting
to um
[Music]
talk about bayesian networks
and uh
often bayesian networks are framed as
only dags so the standard definition
according to these authors the standard
definition of bayesian networks is
usually one directional acyclic directed
graphs
in higher dimension systems
further probabilistic relations can be
recovered from network cyclic properties
and the joint probability of all
variables and this paper shows like for
a two
system
where there's a just a kind of back and
forth between these two x and y
variables here's x y and z in a
three-way loop
and then here's a four-way loop and then
they also look at n order loops so it
can generalize so
what was once only imagined is now
proved
in other words let's not
get too confident about like what can or
can't be done
with one type of model family or the
other because it's just one clever paper
away for their to be an approximation or
to be an exact solution
now we turn to
the other
sense of dcm
and this is dynamical causal models and
so these dcm
can
have graphical structure that also is
directed acyclic graph but
it's a different usage of the term
and so dcm
here we could point to many resources
like fristen at all the 2007s
statistical parametric mapping textbook
or a later paper of fristen at all on
network discovery with dcm
and so i thought that 2011 paper was a
little bit more relevant because it's
about
specifically inferring or discovering
the functional architecture of
distributed systems using dynamic causal
modeling
what does this technique do
it uses bayesian model selection
so comparison of the relative adequacy
and complexity of different bayesian
models to identify the sparcity
structure which is where there are edges
or not
or where there aren't which is the same
thing as where they are
in a graph that is best explaining in
observed time series
the implicit adjacency matrix that's
that spare city structure specifies the
form of the network eg cyclic or acyclic
and then later on we see unlike
conventional approaches to network
discovery dcm permits the analysis of
directed and cyclic graphs
so
dcm is an approach for looking at a time
series that's the dynamic part through
time
and then looking at how variables
statistically cause each other
and so a statistical cause is like when
one thing happens and then at some later
time point there's another thing
happening that's a statistical causal
model like granger causality
we're talking about our model so if
bitcoin price goes up and then later oil
price goes up across the whole time
series so there would be a directed
causal edge
there might be a bi-directional causal
edge or a one-directional causal edge it
doesn't mean that in the real world one
going up caused the other it's just
talking about our time series data so
that's dynamic causal modeling and it
can be applied to neuroimaging data blue
i have a quick question here so um i get
the time series that that makes it
dynamic but i also thought like you
could have functional studies that also
fall into the category of dynamic causal
modeling like gene knockouts right so
like you'd knock out a gene not
necessarily a time
um variation but like a variation in the
graph itself and so you knock out a gene
and then isn't that also dynamical
causal modeling or that's something
different
um one could have like the nodes be
gene expression through time
and then test how
perturbations or counterfactual
network architectures would result in
different
expressions through time
but can you take the time out of it and
have it still be a dynamic model i guess
it's just snapchats right so it's not um
not time series but like gene series i
don't know like knocking out the genes
in the series to make it a dynamic model
if it were just a single
time slot slice
then
it's a little bit unclear what the edges
would reflect
because cause is like effect through
time
in the statistical sense so if it were
just like i have like you know there's
50 people here and 20 people here and 10
people here
it's hard to say where is there a causal
edge whereas if all three were changing
then one could draw these causal edges
okay
now we turn
under the scope of the big question
about modularity two specifically
modularity and the free energy principle
fep
okay
so this is the big topic and kind of the
um
the entree
that benny is bringing to us to discuss
and it's highlighting a really important
issue which is the conceptual
compatibility
of modularity with the free energy
principle
and
it's a
speculation that this conceptual point
may well become
significant in the course of scientific
development of the fep so this is like a
philosopher engaging in a scientific
discussion because there actually is a
lot on the table if we get modularity
right or wrong
so what is the relationship between fep
and modularity
is it compatible
is it necessary sufficient
incompatible like if we have modularity
do we get fep
right that's sufficient do we need
modularity for the fep necessity
if we have it
can we not get the fep incompatibility
are we talking about the modularity of
our world
carving up nature of the joints or of
our scientific statistical models
instrumentalism carving up our models at
the joints that we designed
and then how does our stance or our
perspective
on this topic of modularity and the fep
influence our generative model how we
think and act whether we're the ones
collaborating and writing scientific
papers
or not
and then just to add one more note
despite the great unifying scope fep has
been criticized on account of not
discussing the functional mechanisms of
the brain
so the unifying scope is kind of like
top down
that's the ramstead at all 2018 all of
space and time under the fep envelope
that's the top down description
and then the functional mechanisms are
like those minute particulars that's the
bottom up
components
that build
the system
and that sort of meets in the middle
with the real world systems that people
are always
discussing so
we're talking about how modularity works
with the fep or not any thoughts blue or
dean
well only thing i would add is that it
you can you can be strictly top down
or you can actually
as benny would point out keep an open
mind which means that you've got
some movement for both top down and
bottom up
so
we'll probably get into that more in the
0.1.2
yes
exactly
um
we're now going to go to some
classic citations
so benny writes to address this problem
of modularity in fep
fep theorists may want to provide finer
details about the functional mechanisms
that enable fep so that's how we're
going to make a comeback to colombo at
all 2021 columbo and wright 2016 is by
providing finer detail
in addition to reinvigorating its unifi
unificatory
scope unifying scope maybe that would be
in line with fristen's preceding remarks
that despite its roughness fep may be
developed to provide a guide to brain
functions so we're going to do both
we're going to keep the big scope and
we're going to provide details so let's
look at some of those details
this is also going to provide a really
good introduction to the difference
between the functional and effective
connectivity and connectivity here is
referring to
statistical measurements coming from
brain regions because anatomical
connectivity is just are the pieces
physically connected you know the knee
bones connected to the leg bone that
kind of descriptive anatomical
connectedness
first in 1994
functional and effective connectivity in
neuroimaging a synthesis
so back when we were younger weren't we
the paper reviews the basic distinction
between functional and effective
connectivity in neuroimaging
going over to the origins and
definitions
functional connectivity is defined as
the temporal correlations between
spatially remote neurophysiological
events so that's not the only way to say
it in english or any other language but
we're not talking about a philosophical
um sense of
function
like what does it mean or what is its
teleology we're talking about
statistical
variation in measurements
this definition is operational
very cool
and provides a simple characterization
of functional interactions
the alternative is to explicitly refer
to effective connectivity
i.e the influence that one neuronal
system exerts over another
so
temporal correlation
is things that are um like they could be
uncorrelated in the micro but then
they're both going up together
that would have functional connectivity
whereas effective connectivity would be
looking at how changes in one
at the next time step influence changes
in the other and so those could be like
going in different directions at the
macro
but they could have effective
connectivity
because they influence each other
statistically
let's stay with this fristen 94 theme
but we're not going to go through the
whole thing this is just to show like
what was being discussed and explored
and characterized
about 30 years ago
so keep that in mind we have a long
pheromone trail to catch up with carl on
this is
back in 1994 this is 94.
yeah they had models back then
well they were made of wood but yes
um this is a statistical parametric map
spm
projected onto a brain
and
on this map
of the images
taken through time of a brain that were
fmri in this case
one can take that
data object and find the eigenvalues
and there are mathematical relationships
between functional and effective
connectivity
not going to go into it but it's an
awesome topic explored here and in
several earlier papers and in the 2007
spm textbook and in later papers
what was able to be said
even way back then
well
this is one of the figures
um
[Music]
these are
looking at the
loadings
on different
vectors
so it's a spatial mode that reflects an
eigenvector so it's kind of like a
vector through space and time activity
that explains a large proportion of
variance in the data
and
the first
vector that's this top one
is clearly related to the difference
between word generation even numbered
conditions and word shadowing odd number
scans
so
this was a experimental paradigm where
the person was being asked to do two
different things alternating generate a
word and then shadow a word like i guess
repeat a word that was already said
and then
this vector
which had this activation pattern on the
right in the brain
was
negatively correlated with the odds and
evenly correla and positively correlated
with the even so it's a plausible
mechanistic
statement about the differences in the
activated neuroanatomy
doesn't mean it's simple to interpret
but
it's a vector whose expression is
correlated with something in the
experimental design
like if you did a double-blind study and
these people got the drug and these
people got a different drug
the correlation between them would be
ascribed to the difference that you as
the experimenter imposed
whereas here's an example of another
vector
that declines throughout the entire
experiment
and so that might reflect for example
attention
dropping off through time and so that's
a lot of neural imaging then and now
looking into these summarized um
[Music]
statistical representations of activity
patterns through time
and also for um
later just it's cool to look at some of
these citations like the edelman
citations tonini and sporns 92
these are really
classic citations
so there we were in 94
and then this is a dream of the future
from 94.
so here's
um zargami and firsten
in
2020.
again
talking about effective connectivity
biologically grounded models like
dynamic causal modeling and dynamical
systems theory
so
improving and iterating on those basic
ideas
and then also what does it look like to
apply it and what kinds of conclusions
and statements do scientists make when
just applying these uh
methods
so for example
this paper was in 2019
and it is called
dynamic causal modeling of effective
connectivity
should sound familiar during anger
experience in healthy young men
seven tesla mri imaging study
and so
um
you can read the abstract but they
find that viewing certain kinds of films
leads to activation of certain brain
regions
dot dot dot we propose a model of
effective connectivity associated with
the anger experience based upon dynamic
causal modeling
the findings have implications for
psychiatric disorders
so that's what people do they put people
into scanners they take measurements of
the hemodynamics of the brain
and then
make a statistical model of it and the
edges
that exist across all subjects or only
in the ones who have this diagnosis or
only in these experimental conditions
those edges are interpreted
in a certain way
that's what's on the table but we're
discussing all these techniques
any comments on fristen94 or we'll go to
the other classic
just that effective connectivity is what
i was thinking of like in the gene
network like how are they effectively
connected so it's like makes sense now
yes
another
classic but a more recent one is 2009
firstin's paper again single author
paper
the free energy principle a rough guide
to the brain
so now that's
how long ago 13 years ago
the free energy principle might provide
a comprehensive account of how we
represent the world and come to sample
it adaptively
through action by moving our little eyes
around
the fep provides a mathematical
specification of what the brain is doing
now that starts to sound like realism
right what the brain is doing not
a functional description of the models
we make about the brain
it is suppressing free energy if it uses
gradient descent
and so
um
the box with the questions for future
research
um
are really
still key what optimization schemes does
the brain use these are like still
important questions
and then also um
the domains
of application
it's just
always good to see like what was the
fep's description and scope
13 years ago
some of the images
we've even seen
again and again
with
sometimes some variants
but these are like images that we see
commonly we talk about action to
minimize surprise
and perception to optimize the bound so
this is like the predictive processing
element and this is like the control
theory element
um we talk about the topology of
perception cognition and action
so
suffice to say that there are
equations
figures and it's another great paper on
the long road towards the fep
any comments on 2009 paper
all right
blue would you like to describe
modularity
sure
so um i just wanted to explicitly define
it because we talked about it a little
bit in the abstract and we're going to
talk about it a lot more but um in the
paper the the author defined modularity
as information encapsulation which
dean mentioned earlier
and he says informational encapsulation
holds that when engaged in information
processing the subsystems do not have
access to information processing in
other compartments and information
processing within each subsystem is
constrained within the combination
computational mechanisms of that
subsystems
of that subsystem and so the modules are
then defined by information segregation
um and it's interesting to compare
modularity like is encapsulating
information in a module versus defining
individuality which um
but both like mike levin and the
computational boundary of a self paper
that we did last summer and then um
david krakauer in his 2020 theory about
the information theory of individuality
both
of those authors um
talk about information sharing like
information sharing um like with cells
to form a tissue for example in mike
levin's work and then in the information
theory of individuality paper like up
and down across different levels so that
you can define individuality at any
given level but it talked about how
information is shared
with this bi-directional causation
in that paper and so i think it's
interesting to compare this idea of
informational encapsulation in a module
with these definitions of biological
individuals
very cool like is modularity the same
thing as individuality
how about continue describing maybe in
this discussion on intransitivity
well so i had to like look this up so i
i i just like it i went into the paper
like i just wanted somebody to just
define what does this intransitivity
mean and so the author says the general
insight in is based on the
intransitivity of the passage of
prediction errors
between levels whose information can
affect one another only in cases of
uncertainty and noise
so
i feel like that this is like
intransitivity of information between
the modules like but i it was just not
clear enough for me so then i tried to
look up like what is intransitivity what
is its intransitivity theory and i came
across this really cool paper um which
is 2015 and entropy
intransitivity in theory and the real
world and it
i think it's really different than like
what we're talking about here but it
talked about like uh intransitivity in
terms of preferences and it said the
choice between transitive which are
transitive which are absolute and
intransitive which are relativistic
models depends on the nature of the
processes that these models are expected
to reproduce many people however have a
psychological difficulties in accepting
a relativistic approach expecting an
absolute scale of judgment from bad to
good which can be suitable in some cases
but excessively simplistic in others and
they gave the idea of intransitivity in
game theory and so like an intransitive
game is just rock paper scissors
which obviously like your choice there's
no it's not rock is always good paper is
always good tails never fails it's
always relative to what the other people
are choosing right in this in this game
um and then they really go into like
multi-dimensionality and intransitivity
so he says in the paper coarsening which
is like coarse graining in
multi-dimensional cases becomes strictly
intransitive
and the cases without strict
intransitivity are degenerate either
dimensions are redundant or coarsening
is performed after
merging the fractional variables into
the overall utility instead of
independent questioning for all or some
of the criteria
from a philosophical perspective this
statement can be presented as a
continuum argument for intransitivity
small alterations are commonly
overlooked for secondary parameters but
can be accumulated into critical
differences and so i just thought that
this was cool because it talks about
like philosophy and some things that
we're talking about and relative or like
you know realist versus instrumentalist
but it's completely unrelated and i just
wonder like is it completely unrelated
or can we go back and then like link
intransitivity
full circle into what we're discussing
here today so it was just i put this in
here because i thought it was a cool
paper and in my search for
intransitivity um that's what i ran into
awesome putting a number on something
often makes it seem like whatever you're
putting the number on they are
transitive you know if everybody gets a
score out of 100
then there's a natural order or if we're
ranking policies according to their
expected free energy then there might be
some ordering of policies according to
which ones are best minimizing free
energy and i think this idea of
intransitivity within the graphical
model
what kinds of information are being
passed
and what does it mean and then just more
broadly like you brought up with the
game theory it's very interesting
all right let us continue almost
finishing the first section and get to
modularity fep and the target
of the paper
which is the hippolito and kirchoff
paper
so without intending to map the course
of the evolution of the fep like we will
blue
i will just remark that the assumption
of modularity has been fruitful in the
study of brain functions
and so
keeping an open mind about that
assumption could be fruitful for the fep
too some significant critiques such as
hippolito and kirchhoff 2019 not
withstanding
if you want to read more
definitely check out this paper from
late 2019 by ines and michael and they
are also as well as any of you welcome
to come on and discuss this paper that
could be really cool to like kind of
embody and enact the paper and
are we on the same page or what are our
perspectives even if we are on the same
page
and this paper is engaging in the
discussion of the relationship between
modules and modularity
the main goal of the paper is not to
defy hippolyto and kirchoff's attack
completely
the notion of modularity that benny will
defend is weaker than the notion that
they attack
so
what senses or types of modularity are
we dealing with
what are the stronger and weaker claims
and we'll look at their definition on
the next slide
the main point of the discussion
is that according
following hippolyta on kirchoff the
modest definition of modularity is
neither insignificant nor indispensable
so that made me ask are we seeing a
trend towards
instrumentalism bottom-up weak claims
like the entailment exploration of 34
and deflationary models
and moves away
from
naive or
realist
strong claims
and so that just totally
points to the role of philosophy in an
ongoing scientific domain
because um
things like strong and weak emergence or
entailment relationships and these
discussions on modularity they really
matter for how science is done and how
it's interpreted so it's just really
cool to be seeing that happen
in a new way
again we're not going to go into the
whole argument of hippolyta and kirchoff
check out the paper but
they are going to
consider the three most well articulated
which is funny because that means well
said but also
well jointed
arguments for the view that modularity
and predictive processing work well
together
so predictive processing here is also
referring to kind of that component of
active inference
and they're going to argue that all
three of these arguments for modularity
come up short albeit for different
reasons so they kind of do like a steel
person where they give the strongest
argument for that
attack and then they refute it and the
three arguments they discuss are the
epistemic bayesian courtroom argument
which is just the idea that
court rooms are modular
and cognition's kind of like a courtroom
like the eye is like a witness and then
there's like another witness thereof and
so if that's modular then shouldn't
predictive cognitive architectures be
modular
b the intransitivity argument
which is that the causal influences
across hierarchical levels
are instantiating mechanisms that
implement causal bayesian networks
and they basically say
that is pitching
predictive processing in terms of the
dag
as opposed to
cyclic models
and see the markov blanket argument the
notion that a markov blanket grounds the
idea that predictive processing exhibits
modularity
and so
they are going to explore those and
confuse them as they say
and one of the key points is when
cognitive neuroscience works with an
acyclic markov decision scheme so that's
like the partially observable markov
decision process that we were talking
about earlier
it may
very well be methodologically misguided
why because there's an increasing
tendency within neuroscience to
emphasize recurrent and reciprocal
neuronal processing within the newly
emerging dynamical causal modeling
frameworks
so
how are we going to think about the fact
that the brain does have these feedback
feedback loops
and
square the circle with the dags and the
dcms and
that's kind of the introduction that's
where we're set up which is that
hippolyta and kirchoff have framed
and then
attacked
three pro arguments for modularity
and cognitive architectures related to
predictive processing
benny is going to kind of
take some of that energy and with a
weaker
version
com or a little bit of a different
version not simply stronger or weaker
because that would actually imply
transitivity of strength but with a
slightly different tack
is going to
um
recall us to life
through a discussion of modularity
so this section is only going to have
one
slide on it and then either of you
please uh feel free to add any comments
there's been a long history of debate on
modularity in neuroscience
and fodor who's a very influential
cognitive scientist
define modular cognitive systems
as systems that are domain specific
innately specified hardwired autonomous
and not assembled
that's not exactly the definition of
modular that we've explored in some
other slides but
the words are what they are
and
that is the benny quote about that
functional
isolation between modules is what
defines them so it's kind of like when
there's more connection within than
between then that's modular and so benny
writes the present paper does not intend
to defend fodor's version of the
modularity thesis fully probably because
some of these pieces about like innate
specification hardwiring autonomous
unassembled
take it or leave it it was the 80s
but benny is simply aiming to show that
some critiques of modularity do not need
to undermine the possibility of
informational encapsulation
so
although a falsification
of informational encapsulation leads to
the renunciation of modularity
a defense of partial encapsulation would
not establish a full-blooded form of
modularity so if
you refute encapsulation
you have to renounce modularity
however parcel
or transient encapsulation
doesn't give you strong modularity
claims
however it can be compatible with the
instrumental usage of models that have
modularity
so
those are some of the main arguments
that set bennie up to defend a version
of modularity that's quite modest
and it's almost like after that kind of
a modest deflationary take the question
is really
is there any value
in that definition of modularity at all
so the debate isn't over whether we can
discuss things modularly
if we're going to take this different
tack then really the question is like
does it matter
any comments on section 2
so i don't know i don't want to get too
deep into it maybe better to hold off
for the
dot one but i just wonder about like if
encapsulation so if it's if something's
fully informationally encapsulated like
you know my heart is fully
informationally encapsulated from
my brain like how do you how does a
living system function right so so this
partial encapsulation if that's not
strong enough for modularity like i
don't know how full encapsulation as
possible i just i i don't see it so
yes
section three is entitled a golden
thread free energy principle and so
we just had to go there with a blake
reference because on his gravestone and
one of his most famous lines is
i give you the end of a golden string
only wind it into a ball it will lead
you in at heaven's gate built in
jerusalem's wall and then here's a
drawing that he made with a mythological
character
walking with a golden string
so the general idea according to benny
behind predictive coding is that the
brain uses approximate bayesian
inference to decrease discrepancy
between predictions and inputs
that is one of the
key contentions of the fep
and
the organism's interaction with its
environment can be represented by marco
blankets
here i am using representation and
modeling when speaking of markup
blankets and consider them to be
markovian models so check out
benny's
guest stream appearance i think it's
number one
on markovian monism and
this sentence makes it clear we're
talking about models we're in the realm
of instrumentalism
we're talking about
markovian models
not about whether we're making an
ontologically real claim about markov
blankets like being the structure of
reality so in these models markov
blankets are describing
the conditional independence of internal
and external states
and then it's that fristen innovation
beyond pearl and markov's
to
describe the incoming dependencies as
sensory and the outgoing dependencies as
active states
so
what is the golden thread
the fep is an approach for embroidering
or what creating markov blankets finding
them what is the golden thread
what is the silver thread and golden
needle
so what do you think the illusion means
and what does the fep have to do with it
well i'll speak a little bit on this i
might get it wrong but that's okay we're
still 0.0
i think the predictive coding
as a as an entailment question fits
inside of
the um
what did he call bcc brain
uh
brain brain brain brain brain
i can't find it now in here anyway i
think that i think there's a subtle and
a nuanced difference between what fep is
as a process and as a principle and what
fvp
architecture is and i think that
is what he is trying to bring
to the table
there is a difference between the
architecture or the product that results
from the use of an fep process and the
fe pre fep process itself and once i
figure out my own notes here i can speak
to what that bcc is but i'll i'll shut
up for a second
very well
interesting to describe the difference
between the principle and the realized
architecture
section 4
the track of a storm
so here's another
single slider
so there's some apparent tension between
the modularity thesis and the predictive
architecture
so that's
what kirchoff and hippolyta described
while the thesis of modularity points in
the direction of segregation and
encapsulation
the predictive architecture grounds the
integration of information
in a hierarchical top-down architecture
that unifies the mechanisms of
cognition perception and action under
the fpp
so it's like what blue just said
wait if it's encapsulated and defined by
its separation
then how is it part of this integrated
whole
well
howie in 2013 the book the predictive
mind
and other people in other places have
suggested that this conditional
independence between
the various levels of the hierarchical
structure of predictive coding under fep
could be construed
along the lines of functional
segregation and informational
encapsulation which is why fodor was
brought up earlier
drayson
argued that the predictive architecture
can be modeled in terms of this causal
probabilistic dependency
where different nodes could influence
the um adjacent levels but there isn't
global transitivity so like the lower
most nodes
are not influencing all just the ones
directly above them
however the hippolyto and kirchoff paper
challenge
that vertical and horizontal account so
the vertical account is like the
multi-scale nested systems the
horizontal account is like the
collective behavior interactions across
within a level and so they aim to refute
this account of functional informational
modularity
according to hippolyta and kirchoff and
let's
hear from them if it's not the case
the intransitivity argument for
modularity is based on dax
however they're going to argue that dags
are not suitable for that kind of
modeling
because
the brain has these cyclic mechanisms
and so dags have to be replaced by
cyclic models which don't have the
limitations of dags
um and then with respect to the markov
blanket point benny asserts that
hippolito and kirchoff argue that
the argument from markov blankets is of
little avail to establishing modularity
he will
get to both of those arguments he kind
of doesn't really worry about the
courtroom as much but the intransitivity
and the markovian blanket
arguments are what benny's gonna focus
on but
first
remark on the importance of scientific
models
so
kind of a fun tack but that's section
four
yes please d
yeah so i found out
bcc is brain's cognitive capacities
that's how he described it in the paper
so i don't think it's a rock paper
scissors issue either i believe that
predictive coding
is entailed by the brain's cognitive
capacities
i believe that the brain's cognitive
capacities are entailed by the free
energy principle so it sounds like
you've got a rock paper scissors but
that's not the same as the free energy
principles architecture
being entailed by predictive coding
i would have to diagram that out for you
but that's where he's saying it's not an
intransitivity argument
and that's that's just notes to me
and that's where i kind of j ran into
his corner even though i
i want to actually do a paper later this
year a review of one of hippolyta's
papers on an action that i think is
fantastic in instrumentalism but that
this was the moment where
it it was clear to me that it's not an
intransitivity argument because back
that what axel pointed out to we have to
know what entails what
very cool
section five
a knock at the door
models and
modeling we
we really do need to do that joke stream
knock knock jokes like you know
who's there i don't know who are you
expecting
who do you prefer
um
in this
section
benny is going to describe some comments
on modeling
he writes i do not think we can find a
reliable model independent handle on the
architecture of the brain
so it's kind of like saying
if we're going to science
we're going to model
so let's not think that we could science
without modeling
the general insight is that the
interface of scientific theories and
their target systems
takes place through scientific modeling
so theories about the brain
the brain itself and then the edge is
the scientific modeling now the brain is
like a special and fascinating system
because it can be
reflexively modeling itself but if you
think about um
theories of pendulum pendulums theory of
pendulum
and then
the target system of the actual pendulum
it's pretty clear to see where the
modeling relation comes into play
however again it gets kind of strange
loopy with the brain
and benny is drawing upon various works
some of it is the weisberg work on like
simulation and similarity using models
to understand the world
and also some of benny's earlier work
for example the ways in which markov
blankets are construed as scientific
models and
similar points have been discussed by
mel andrews 2021 that was actin 14.
so
scientists
are making and applying
models
and so we're not going to break out of
that
vip room in plato's cave
so
we have different kinds of models and
maybe some of them are preferable but
like if your argument is predicated on
breaking free of a given scientific
model
it is um
something to hear if you think you have
it
dean
so this is it got interesting for me
here too because if you
if you look for example at a slice of
time in an fmri image you could be
focused
on
the concentration of heat
in different areas of the brain that
would be one bit of information that you
could take away or
you could look at the
proportion
of
blood in different areas of the brain
which is going to tell you a little bit
of different information than the
the actual concentration of heat that
heat bump per se
and so i was kind of curious
who
who is a modeler here because he talks
about we can't take our we can't take
the the observer out of the observation
so again
what relative what relative bit of
information do we tend to hone in on or
or do we think is the the
the more
um
priority information to take away from
one of these slices of time
representations
that was really important to me right
here because if you think of
encapsulation as that sort of frenetic
image a few slides backward all the
brain is is chopped up like
like here's the bacon and here's the ham
and right the different parts of the pig
you're you're you're choosing what it is
that you think
is the way of of of encapsulating but i
don't think that's what he's talking
about
we'll
explore it but yes
taking this kind of a really strong
principled stance on scientific modeling
means that we can always ask who is
doing the modeling why and so actually
it's not just this sterile philosophical
point
it really brings us to consider the
social and the operational aspects of
science so it's very important like
socio-technical
point
section six
the game made
the intransitivity argument
okay we're not gonna go through all the
details here we might have time in the
dot one and two but
there uh
benny is going to focus on hippolyto and
kirchoff's
specific reply to the intransitivity
argument
that is centering the distinction
between the
directed acyclic graphs
and directed cyclic graphs
benny is going to argue
that these two kinds of statistical
models do different things
it turns out they actually also map onto
the difference between functional and
effective connectivity
and so applying one sort of the model
dag or the cyclic model in a specific
situation is a matter of practice
practical
exigency and methodological
consideration as well as the goals in
the interest of the modeler so it's like
we're 100 miles down choosing a model
free freeway
and then whether you take this slight
difference between
one topology of graphical model that's
quantitative versus a different topology
maybe that is not going to be super
philosophically impactful because we
already have taken like the big pill
which was making a scientific model or
making a graphical quantitative model
um
[Music]
there's a citation to the fristin visa
hobson 2020 paper
that also describes like where the
cyclic versus acyclic are
uh preferable
and
uh benny recaps and just basically to
summarize there is no universal reason
for extolling dags over dcms
because the focus on functional
connectivity or effective connectivity
is a matter of explanatory predictive
goals and interests
so
scientists are using different kinds of
models
and so maybe we should pull back to
scientists use models
and think about the implications of that
rather than try to
finesse out some philosophical
implications from the very specific kind
of last mile modeling choices
dcms
can do certain things whereas dags can
do other things
which one of these approaches can be
used to analyze data in the context of
the fep we're going to discuss it
in 35.1
benny says i do not think hipolito and
kirichoff 2019 are bound to concede a
non-realist reading of dcm
rather the critique
of how h and k compute the
intransitivity argument is pointed at
their unjustified partiality towards
dcms
so
it's like if you could just scapegoat
the
dag
then the dcm is the savior
but if both of them are just types of
scientific models that are chosen
situationally operationally as thriston
described then
there is no
savior model coming in to save the day
dcms are formal devices
and then there's a citation to the
emperor's new markov blankets with yella
at all
live stream number 20.
and so drawing attention to the
difference between dags and dcms which
are complementary modeling tools as we
discussed earlier they're defined as
complementary
could not confuse the intransitivity
argument so
if we have already committed
to the instrumental perspective
so we're talking about our model not
about the world
then
the difference between different
modeling approaches is purely
situational or operational
and so
all scientific models have roughly
similar philosophical grounding or
they're part of a broad category
with respect to this intransitivity
argument
nice
philosophy and
interesting points
okay
column in the storm
the indispensability of modularity and
the indispensability of scientific
models oh i wonder if there's going to
be like a parallelism between
models and modularity and here's like a
person
in their markov bubble
in the storm
this section focuses on a realist
interpretation of dcm in terms of
dynamical causal models
so
even instrumentalists
can
bat both ways
you know we're not obliged to never talk
about stances that in one certain
situation we didn't prefer it's just
really
wide-ranging
intellectual exploration that's being
characterized here
and here benny does play on a little bit
of a acronym play which is that dcm
applies to dynamic causal modeling as
well as directed cyclic modeling
so cyclic graphs or the dynamic causal
graph
and
he'll argue through an example that
we're going to discuss not today with
alice and bob
he argues that the modularity in the
context of dcm
it's not as strong as the fodorian
isolationist concept but
in interesting and important ways
it's going to be enough
and so a moderate form of modularity is
retained
and uh
hippolyto and kirchoff argue that this
weakened notion of modularity is
explanatory vacuous it's empty and there
would be no reason for keeping it
and that's
the bone of contention
he's going to dissent
and say that the benefit of this modest
notion of modularity is
remarkable
so
that's the claim any comments on section
seven
what would happen if we couldn't
categorize
then it would be impossible to give a
categorical response to that question
and
and a lot more right like that that's
basically what this comes down to
doesn't mean that things aren't
arbitrary and not necessarily
put into into the correct silos but but
there is a great benefit i don't think
it's dispensable our our capacity to
categorize doesn't mean we always
are
obliged to do it but when we do do it is
there a benefit
yes is there a cost
maybe
but if we if we took it away
what would what would then what would
the world look like then
a triangle is a triangle as a triangle
right
there would be no specificity then
interesting we'll talk more about
categorization models and the parable of
alice and bob yeah section eight
still knitting markov blankets
so um
here
they return
to
this idea of the vertical
insulation and the horizontal insulation
like there's encapsulation laterally
collective behavior and then
encapsulation like an onion like a
multi-scale system
so
that's very interesting and this is also
where we get to this point about the
scale-free or skill-friendly nature of
markov blankets
um
the main reason that h and k resist this
argument
about the markov blankets
is based on the fact that the
regimentation of states into markov
blankets is scale free
so it can range across scales maybe even
that is already scale friendly
um
because markow blankets are scale free
they do not imply insulation and thus
the modularity thesis does not receive
support from them
and so
benny concedes yeah it's true mark-out
blankets can be applied to basically a
wide range of phenomena however this is
overlooking a subtle point
markov blankets
in the abstraction in principle are
scale-free there's no inherent
constraint on their size and scope
linear models are inherently
a priori scale-free it could be
centimeters versus the gdp it could be
astronomical units versus temperature
like it doesn't have a tie-in to a
certain spatial temporal scale or any
feature for a linear model or for a
markov blanket
however
q dean from stage left or you know
running in from the audience
their application or imputation
to various target systems will impose a
definite scale on markov blankets to
make a long story short
in the context of their application
under fep
not in the context of fep
markov blankets are not necessarily
scale-free mathematical models because
they're being used in models
so even though the formal tools could be
scale-free
application mandates calibrating to a
certain scale
if that's the case and
it seems like it is
then
counter arguments based upon the
scale-free nature of markov blankets
could not undermine arguments from
markovian formalisms soundly so this is
really nicely framed and placed
in space and time dean what do you think
about that
well i'm still as i said i i did first
of all i want to
i want to make sure to disclaim this i
never saw this paper until three days
ago four days ago
so
my guess my what my wag about scale
friendly and and sort of
whether that was something we should
consider it was nice to read this and
have somebody else go maybe it's
something we should consider i'm going
to leave it at that because i don't know
if somebody's going to come along and
disprove that and and you know because
if that's
if it's if it's falsifiable that um
calibrating doesn't matter and and
categorizing doesn't matter i'm open to
hearing that too
but in the meantime i think it's
something that if we don't
recognize the difference between the
abstraction
and
that
thing that we're focusing on right now
we can
get lost in the idea that a triangle is
a triangle is a triangle and nothing
else matters
blue anything you want to add on this
section
yeah i mean i really think that um
i mean it just
hits the nail on the head like we're the
ones
like putting the markov blanket on
something and so like just because
something can be
you know modeled using a markov blanket
doesn't necessarily mean it doesn't
scale and and like
things don't mark off blanket themselves
right like so i mean even like my layer
of skin like cells are popping off and
new cells are adding on all the time and
so like there's
it's not a hard boundary it's not a
solid boundary it's very fluid like what
goes in and out of a markov blanket so i
think like our imputation of a markov
blanket on a system i mean yeah they're
scale free means you can impute them on
any system at any scale
so so maybe scale friendly is is
um the way to go but it's not like the
blanket itself is scale free i mean all
blankets are are composed of stitches
right like so are you using big stitches
or little stitches or like different
layers of cloth or or what so i don't
know it's it's uh i don't know i think
it really
drives it home
yeah
and uh the paper
was
i mean we can double check but it's from
december
21 so
we have proof of live stream dean that
you know
you were there
um
can i just say one last because i
completely agree with with what blue
just said i was i was never of an
opinion that that markov blanket isn't
scale free of course it is
and it's kind of like saying they're
subject matter experts of course there
are
but as we had in the in the conversation
with dr fristen
you could also say that there's a
prediction matter expert
like all i'm asking is for people to
consider that there could be both
and they could be running in parallel
that's i wasn't trying to push back in
the sense that you know people are wrong
what i was saying is what what else
could we include to phil
fill in the wholeness of what is
happening here that's all i was
trying to point out and i and again it
we could take active inference and and
focus it completely on the minimizing of
free energy and getting what we're
attending to or we can talk about the
availability piece and what
for example when we're having new people
on board
to our lab how how we make that that
entry point so
so relationship based we could do that
we could make
for them we could make them prediction
that matter experts before they even
realize it in themselves now whether we
do that or not it's not up to me but we
could so that's what i was trying to
bring up and that's what i like about
this paper
great
last section last content slide isn't it
something they say like if the newspaper
article
ends with a question mark i forget which
one is it the it's always yes or it's
always no but
the footsteps die out forever
so this is a summary in the ninth
section
benny challenges the main points of
hippolito and kirchoff
hippolyta and kirchoff confuded the
modularity thesis
so benny is salvaging the modularity
thesis from the pincer attack of
hippolito and kirchoff
to support the argumentation of the
paper
benny draws upon the indispensability of
a model-based conception of modularity
that's where that kind of science and
society angle and philosophy angle came
into play
benny argues that dags and dcms are
complementary models
and the choice between them is
operational it's pragmatic
it's not
um metaphysical per se
so modeling is situational we can take a
deflationary approach
even to how we think about science
benny argues that when
we think about dynamic causal modeling
there is
modularity because of how the
statistical model pulls out differential
coupling between brain areas
and that's not a statement about the
brains the statement about the model
benny also challenges
hippolito and kirchhoff's answer to the
argument from the markovian formalism
by showing that although these models
are in principle scale free in order to
represent any specific target system
they have to be associated with
interpretations that do give definite
scales so the markov blanket formalism
is conceptually skill-free but any
realization application is scale
specific thus skill friendly tickles 21
at best
personal communication
already and basically we're exciting the
live stream soon yeah
benny closes with just saying it doesn't
undermine the claims
and this isn't like a radical pro
pro-modular thesis
it's not the isolation of brain regions
and they're each like virtual machines
that are totally separated
the only point that comes to light by
our enterprise in this paper
is that the debate over modularity needs
to take the role of scientific models
into account and a model relative
conception of modularity cannot be waved
away
easily
so
it is a great service and an interesting
paper in form and function
we have an empty slide for the
implications and questions we have the
early slide where with um
what we're going to discuss
in 35.1 and 35.2
and
it was an awesome discussion so
if you have any final comments now would
be a good time
do you think that um
when you get people who've worked
together as this author and the person
and the two people that he was kind of
pushing back against
do you think when they take it into this
kind of a formal setting of paper
writing that that changes their
relationship
fundamentally
that's one i mean i i could i suppose we
could only ask the authors themselves
but does it have to be a debate
necessarily does it have to be drama
necessarily or is there is there kind of
a moving forward hand-in-hand part to
this i'm not
seeing
it's a really interesting question i'm
sure
scientists and
all kinds of different people are going
to have different answers but
i think about the papers
in their exact phrasing as like
pheromones
digital stigma g in the literature
corpus and then the person is like the
nest mate who is weaving on so any
artifact is going to be made by that
person in the past so i could be like
talking to blue
and it's like oh yeah you know knight
2018 said this
or
you know but you just said this but but
didn't
night 2009
say this
it's not a contradiction
it's just like the trajectory and the
pheromone deposition of
active and complex entities and so i
think that that i hope is the best of
both worlds which is we can humanize
kirchoff and hippolyto and benny and
all the humans involved and take like a
compassionate and even friendly
um tack
while also being very scrutinizing
of the specifics of the knowledge
artifacts that people leave because a
lot of times there is like a gray zone
where it'll say something in text but
then oh if you're in the club then you
know that they actually meant something
else or you got to read between the
lines with the methods or you have to
read between the lines with the
citations
and um
that's kind of a conflation of the
person and the argument
like when people give an overly
charitable reading or even try to
insinuate things that weren't there in
the initial text because they want to
uphold their legend
of person
and rather we can just kind of
separate those two in how we model
the generative process and the generated
product
i just think that there's so much you
can learn when you're wrong
and that doesn't mean you want to be a
serial mistake maker but i don't think
anybody that's publishing is looking to
do that either
but if you're comfortable if you're
actually comfortable with putting wrong
answers out there
and having put people kind of prove that
you're wrong but you're comfortable with
that
i think that makes a huge
a huge difference at least in terms of
the culture that you're participating in
it's a lot safer if you can if you can
throw stuff out
at in in four weeks or five weeks time
somebody can say
no dean you were wrong we got to take
that citation down
i wouldn't take it down i would leave it
up i would simply say no in that moment
i i thought it was right and now
i now i've updated my generative model
yeah it's like showing your work like
here's what i knew at this time and this
is what leads me to my conclusions
and then someone says well you missed
this paper from
[Music]
okay
then that updates
the next round of pheromone deposition
exactly blue any last comments
good yeah it's a fun start to 22. and
it's the two architectures 2022 second
year of active lab
two two two two two two two is coming up
i mean
it just couldn't it couldn't get any
better that's great
thank you folks yeah appreciate you and
everyone